[Music]
there's an ongoing controversy about the
relationship between ideas and events
some people say that it's the events of
history that provoke new ideas where
others insist that it's new ideas that
change the course of history
well I think this is one of those false
dilemmas sort of like the Chicken and
the Egg because I think we can
understand that there is a symbiotic
relationship between events and ideas
where events can provoke new ideas and
new ideas can certainly shape future
events one thing I think we can be sure
of and that is that ideas
have consequences
and I think it would be a fascinating
study to look at the culture in which we
live today or to look at the history of
the world
in the last two thousand years and Trace
the impact of the ideas of Aristotle
down to the present day
because certainly we are still living in
an atmosphere where we are living out
some of the consequences of his ideas
now in theology Luther
when he referred to John Calvin
he simply referred to Calvin as
the theologian
he obviously there are many theologians
in the 16th century but when Luther
spoke of the Theologian everybody knew
of whom he was speaking namely of Calvin
likewise in the jargon of philosophers
in Western history when they simply
speak of
the philosopher
it's obvious who they have in mind it is
the philosopher Aristotle
now we know that Aristotle was a pupil
and disciple of Plato
he was the Academy's most illustrious
alumnus
but Plato didn't refer to Aristotle
simply by calling him the philosopher
rather Plato's pet name for Aristotle
was
the brain
now
Aristotle had a profound love and
virtual hero worship of his teacher
Plato
and Plato obviously had some affection
for Aristotle but the historians will
agree
that the degree of affection that
Aristotle had for Plato was not returned
in kind by Plato to his student
and one of the sad notes of that
relationship was that when it came time
for Plato to choose a successor for
himself in the academy on two occasions
he passed over Aristotle and that very
much hurt Aristotle so that Aristotle
left the academy and went out and
started his own school called the lyceum
which was what he called the peripatetic
school because his method of teaching
was to walk around as he was lecturing
hence the word peripatetic also
Aristotle was a bibliophile that's not
an illegal crime or anything like that
that just means somebody who loves books
and he possessed many books and spent a
lot of time reading books and Plato
didn't give his full approval to that
Plato thought that people could become
too bookish he favored The Interchange
of live dialogue and discussion as his
mentor
Socrates had instructed him
Plato was also known for his uh plain
style of dressing somewhat casual
whereas Aristotle became known as a
Dandy he had very expensive haircuts and
he was adorned with with fine jewelry
and he liked to have tailor-made robes
in which to dress and so they had a
little bit of conflict at that level as
well but the big point of debate between
Plato and Aristotle which has defined
the difference of platonism and
aristotelianism ever since was over
Plato's theory of ideas and consequently
over Plato's theory of recollection so I
mean when two philosophers disagree
fundamentally at the level of
metaphysics and at the level of
epistemology that's a pretty significant
disagreement
the problem that vexed Aristotle in the
thinking of Plato was the problem of
dualism Plato had sought to bring a
synthesis or Harmony between the
thinking of barmenides and heraclitus to
resolve this tension between the
concepts of being and becoming as I've
pointed out and the way he solved the
problem was to speak of two different
worlds the ideal world and the world of
the receptacle the realm of being and
the realm of becoming as I said his
theme song may have been the song that
was popular earlier in this Century that
was called two different worlds we live
in two different worlds you maybe
remember that some of you do you do
but in any case that vexed Aristotle
because
he didn't see this as really escaping
the problem
of dualism
and Aristotle had a singular passion for
Unity
he had a deep desire to have a unified
theory of knowledge that would
incorporate all of the different
Sciences biology and physics and
astronomy and ethics and Aesthetics and
all the rest
and
by unifying them
without any kind of leftover dualism and
we may add just as a point of historical
interest that Aristotle also had some
students as Plato had and his most
famous student was a man by the name of
Alexander the Great of course Alexander
the Great is not known to the world as a
philosopher in the tradition of Socrates
Plato and Aristotle but rather we think
of him as one of the most important
conquerors of antiquity but what
motivated Alexander the Great in his uh
Conquest was to bring
a unified culture to the ancient world
that we call the process of
hellenization he wanted to impose the
greatness of Greek culture including the
Greek language on all of the people whom
he conquered and it as as I have
mentioned in the past when he set out on
his world Conquest he took with him a
whole what would be a division of
soldiers who were scientists who were
there along with the rest of the
soldiers for the specific purpose of
gathering flora and fauna to be
classified back in the school of the
lyceum under the direction of Aristotle
to advance the cause of Science in fact
it's been said that the most expensive
scientific expedition in all of world
history
up to
the NASA space exploration program in
modern America was the military
Expeditions of Alexander the Great but I
mentioned that only in passing to say
here is one of those cases where ideas
have consequences
where the idea of unity that drove
Aristotle was incorporated in the
military strategies of Alexander so he
lived out the philosophical ideal
that's only one of many many
modern results of the thinking of
Aristotle well in addressing the problem
of dualism
when trying to bring everything into
Unity
Aristotle developed
what we call his theory of substance
Plato had his theory of ideas
Aristotle had his theory of substance
and what
Aristotle meant by this is that all
individual entities everything
that exists in this world
exists as a primary substance
now he said two very important things
about these individual entities remember
the concrete entities that we find in
this world according to Plato were
called receptacles they were imperfect
copies
of the real ideas that exist in this
other world in the ideal world
for Aristotle the individual objects and
entities and things that we encounter in
this world are real
and they are substantial
and that every substance
is comprised of two aspects or two
things
matter
and form
sometimes Aristotle's philosophy is
referred to as the theory of form
and I would say that there's no element
of Aristotle's thought that has been
more perplexing to later philosophers
who have sought to analyze and
understand the depths of his thinking
then his concept of form and I'll just
mention in passing that even to this day
there's an ongoing debate among experts
in Aristotelian philosophy about exactly
what Aristotle meant by his concept of
form
but in this idea of substance that he
distinguishes between matter and form he
finds the resolution of the ancient
problem of being and becoming
in being and becoming
I remember in Plato being is found in
the idea
up here
and becoming
in the receptacle or material things
down here
for Aristotle
being and becoming are found in each
individual entity
every substance that there is
contains within it
both matter and form
is that which gives the object or the
subject it's being
without
participating in being without
containing being
whatever is couldn't be so that you
couldn't have any real things or real
objects unless there was some being
within them
but also things in this world physical
things material things as we know them
also have elements of change elements of
becoming and that
is part of the matter of a thing
let me see if I can illustrate this in
our own contemporary ways of thinking
we talk as Christians about a human
person as being made up
of two distinct substances or what we
call a substantial dichotomy a duality
not a dualism but a duality of body and
soul
and if you don't have a body okay then
something is lost from your entity and
if you have no soul you couldn't live at
all and so for Aristotle within each
object
there was matter
and form
and the form is the eternal
being
and the matter is that which is changing
and is the the locus of potential now
let's talk about those terms the other
language that Aristotle was fond of
using
was the language of actuality and
potentiality
anything that is in a state of becoming
is experiencing potential
potentiality
it is changing it is moving from one
state to another and insofar as it is
moving it is actualizing part of its
potential
but actuality
is a characteristic of form or of being
now again let me illustrate this in
simple terms
have you ever wondered why it is when
you plant an acorn in the ground
that what germinates and Sprouts up from
that acorn
is an oak tree
and not an elephant
or
when two people mate
and one is inseminated by the other
why is it that The Offspring of this
Union
is not a grasshopper
why do things produce after their kind
that was a question that Aristotle was
asking
and so he would say that the form of
humanness
is contained within every person
and the form of elephant-ness is
contained within every elephant and the
form of oak tree nests is contained
within every acorn
there is this inner being what he called
an intellicy you don't need to remember
that technical term that is what moves
or directs
the particular object
to
actualize its potential
an acorn is actually an acorn but
potentially an oak tree
and that which determines its
potentiality is the form that is found
within the acorn it has the form of Oak
treiness
the human seed has the form of humanness
and that's why we produce other human
beings and not elephants
now when it comes to uh
to this theory of course it is
important also to see that Aristotle
makes another distinction about
substance
and it's this he makes a distinction
between what he calls substance and
accidents
not accidents which are unfortunate
mishaps but accidents
now he's saying that every physical
object
has substance
which in turn has matter and form okay
and
accidents which I'm going to illustrate
by these little lines
the accidents are the external
perceivable qualities of an object
the accidents of this
substance which we call chalk
include whiteness
cylindricalness
hardness
flakiness
and so on when you look at a piece of
chalk those are the things that you
notice or see you can't penetrate with
the naked eye into the molecular
structure of this chalk or even less are
you able to perceive its Atomic makeup
or subatomic makeup you don't see the
metaphysical substance of the thing you
think see merely its accidents
external perceivable qualities
ideas have consequences
every day somewhere in the world
a priest is celebrating the mass
and in the Roman Catholic Church
the church believes that in the miracle
of the mass
the miracle of transubstantiation takes
place
and how does the church Define
transubstantiation but the change or
transformation of substance
when they start the mass you have bread
and wine ordinary
Earthly substances
and that bread has this substance of
breadness and the accidents of bread it
looks like bread it tastes like bread it
feels like bread because it is bread
and likewise with the wine it looks like
wine tastes like wine feels like wine
sounds like wine if you spill it on the
floor
because it is wine it has the substance
of wine therefore it has the accidents
of wine
but the miracle is this it's a double
miracle
in the miracle of the mass through the
prayer of consecration
Rome defines the the miracle is this
that in transubstantiation
the substance of the bread
is changed into the substance of the
body of Christ
while
the accidents of bread remain
and the substance of the wine is changed
into the substance of the blood of
Christ but the accidents of wine remain
in other words it still looks like Bread
and Wine tastes like Bread and Wine
sounds like Bread and Wine and all the
rest but it really is no longer Bread
and Wine because the substance of it
it's real stuff has been changed into
the substance of the body and blood of
Christ
so that you have the substance of one
thing
and the without its accidents
and the accidents of another thing
without its substance
you have the substance of the body and
blood of Christ but you can't see them
so you have the substance of Christ
without the accidents of Christ then you
have the accidents of bread and wine
without the substance of bread and wine
that's why I said it's a double Miracle
now of course Aristotle believed and it
would take a miracle to do that because
he believed in the nature of things that
all substances always are
co-present with their accidents and
where you see the accidents of something
you can be sure that it has the
substance of that same thing underneath
it if it walks like a duck and quacks
like a duck that is if it has the
accidents of Darkness you can be sure it
has the substance of Darkness as well
but I only mentioned that in passing to
show you one way in which Aristotle's
thinking is still impacting the world
every single day in fact in 1965 the
Roman Church had a crisis because on the
one hand of the Dutch catechism and the
second of the writings of a Dutch
Theologian Who challenged the formula of
transubstantiation and one of the change
at the trans signification which
ultimately resulted in a Papal
encyclical of 1965 by Paul VI entitled
mysterium fide in which he said not only
does the church maintain the ancient
concept of transubstantiation but
insists upon on retaining the formula
which formula was Aristotelian
in its uh in its
articulation so this idea of substance
philosophy and the distinction between
substance and accidents has had a
long-standing impact on the history of
idea of ideas now
so far we've talked about substance
having form and matter
for Aristotle it would be impossible for
Pure matter to exist
in and of itself
because it would be pure becoming it
would be pure potentiality it would be
potentially everything but actually
nothing
so you can't have
pure independent matter
but for Aristotle it is possible to have
pure form
which would be pure being
or pure actuality
and when we reach that point in his
thinking we come face to face with
Aristotle's creative and Innovative
concept of God
as pure form which we'll look at in our
next session